<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and faithful warning unto the people and inhabitants of Bristol and unto the rulers, priests, and people of England ... that they might prepare to meet the Lord ... / ... Charles Baily.</title>
            <author>Bayley, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1473D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16496</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12164783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12164783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55273</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55273)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 857:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and faithful warning unto the people and inhabitants of Bristol and unto the rulers, priests, and people of England ... that they might prepare to meet the Lord ... / ... Charles Baily.</title>
                  <author>Bayley, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Postscript signed: R.B.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Judgment.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55273:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55273:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE AND Faithful VVarning UNTO The People and Inhabitants of BRISTOL, AND Unto the Rulers, Prieſts and People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in general, that they might prepare to meet the Lord, whoſe Judgments are even pouring out upon the Head of the Tranſgreſſour.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſome QUERIES which deeply concern all who are in Authority in the Nation, to conſider of.</p>
            <p>With a brief Account of ſome Tryals and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which the Author hereof hath ſuffered and ſuſtained at the hands of unreaſonable men in his Travel and Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſince his youth up, until this day: VVhereunto is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a Declaration, briefly treating of his Travels and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Popes Dominions, in and for the Truth of God; which may be both ſeaſonable and profitable unto the unprejudic'd Reader, who ſimply deſireth to know the Truth, from the lies and ſlanders which are caſt upon us who are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as having been falſly accuſed of being <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> or popiſhly affected.</p>
            <p>Given forth in <hi>Newgate</hi> Priſon of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> by a ſufferer for the Truth of God, called CHARLES BAILY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55273:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55273:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Upright-hearted &amp; unprejudic'd READER, In any place where this may come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE occaſion of my writing of this which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth is this: I being a man of ſufferings, bonds and afflictions attending me on every hand, theſe ſeveral yeares, as one who turneth not his back from the ſmiter, nor his check from him that plucketh off the haire, having indeed learned of the Father, how to be a Companion and fellow ſufferer with the man of ſorrow, who was well acquainted with griefs, as being rejected of all (that was and is of this world); I ſay it being ſo that the Lord hath ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated me from my mothers womb, &amp; hath made me like minded unto the Son of his love, by revealing him in me, though few there be which know it, which is the very cauſe why I have been ſo reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and rejected on every ſide, ſome ſaying one thing of me, and ſome another; and for the moſt part, the Cry of the blind world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Prieſts is, that I am a Jeſuite, or a Popiſh Prieſt, though it is not unknown unto many thouſands (in this Nation) how that I have been a deep ſufferer in <hi>Rome</hi> (my ſelf) by the hands of that Idolatrous Crew, who earneſtly ſought my life, and not only mine, but thoſe alſo who were of my perſwaſion; and had not the Lord ſtopped and limited their bloody minds, and intents, we had never eſcaped their hands, for as farre as they were ſuffered to act they did not ſpare, but did hang one of my Deare Brethren (whoſe name was called <hi>John Luffe</hi>), who was a fellow-traveller with <hi>John Parrot,</hi> whom they alſo did uſe very cruelly, not beſeeming modeſty to utter; the ſubſtance of which I know that the King, and and many of the Nobles of this Nation (ſo called) are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, and of his long Impriſonment, which was neer the ſpace of 3 Yeares, wanting but ſome few Dayes; for whoſe ſake (in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55273:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>bowels of Gods Everlaſting love) I was drawn from the <hi>Indies,</hi> where I was a ſojourner neer <hi>14</hi> Yeares, and being drawn from thence (as I ſaid) in the bowels of Gods Love, I had not rest in my ſpirit (night nor day) until I arrived at <hi>Rome,</hi> where I was made willing to tender my life for his, though I had never ſeen his face with my natural eyes; for which cauſe I was (by reaſon of my importunity in that buſineſſe to the Cardinal) caſt into priſon in their Inquiſition houſe, where I was ſecurely kept, and ſtrictly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, concerning the ground and cauſe of my coming there, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of our Practiſes and Principles, unto which I did give anſwer (in great ſimplicity of heart) which would be too long here to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat: They much queſtioned who was our head, and who was the firſt that preached our Religion? and whether we had any thing as from <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Luthe?</hi> and how long our Religion had been? I anſwered, nay, we held not, nor had not our Religion from them, but Christ was our only teacher and head, and we are all Brethren: As for the antiquity of our Religion, I ſaid it was ſince <hi>Abel,</hi> the firſt that ſuffered in innocency; though one of the Jeſuites was ſo blind as to ſay that <hi>Abel</hi> was before Chriſt, (in his anſwer to me before many witneſſes) for which I reproved him. This is but little, as a touch in brief, of what paſſed between us, for I do believe that it tooke up the writing of ſeveral ſheets of paper: And when they ſaw that they could not inſnare me, then they went to their old murthering queſtion (about their Sacrament): I told them that in the Scripture there was no ſuch word truely tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated: And when they ſaw how that I ſaw their deceit in it, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded no further (in that particular): And it being ſo that this writing may happen to come into the hands of thoſe deluded people, I may here in brief ſhew their deceit in that thing, it being the thing for which many ſimple in heart have been barbarouſly murdered &amp; maſſacred: And here this bloody generation ground their deceit in this particular thing in the Scripture, Where the word (Miſtery) is ſpoken, they tranſlate it Sacrament; and when I queſtioned them about it, they ſaid how that <hi>Miſtery</hi> ſignified a holy thing, which I proved to be falſe for I told them there was the <hi>Miſtery of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which was neither Sacrament, nor holy. And after they had tryed me many wayes (in that bloody City; in which time I was kept for the moſt part with ſo little of their natural ſuſtenance, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55273:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>much notice was taken of it; for it was ſo, that after I was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Inquiſition to the hoſpital of mad men, I was put in the publick view of all ſcorners and Jeerers, as one who was mocked and derided of all, as they ſaid I was a ſtrange kind of man, come out of <hi>England,</hi> of the Sect of the <hi>Tremolantes,</hi> that was as much as to ſay, of the Sect of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which people I did with a Cheerful heart there acknowledge to be the only people of the Lord, which thing I can never diſſent from, whether in life or death, though reproachfully called by the name of Sectarians (as of old the true Chriſtians were). And after I was thus publickly viewed and known by means of the many people that came to that place to ſee the diſtracted men, amongſt whom I was alſo held in Chains, I ſay, after this the Lord required me to faſt, as a witneſſe againſt their murthering of my Brother; for after they had murthered him they ſaid he ſtarved himſelf to death; for as they themſelves ſaid he did, and dyed, even ſo the Lord cauſed me to do, and live, which thing for ever ſtands written in the book of Heaven as a witneſſe againſt them, and all that bloody Generation where-ever they are, and alſo againſt their hypocritical Faſtings (for whileſt they pretend to faſt, they feaſt themſelves with the choyceſt &amp; beſt of the creation) which in obedience to the Lord, I continued in about <hi>20</hi> dayes, without any natural ſuſtenance (except water), which did ſo amaze them that they themſelves could not but confeſſe it to be more than a natural thing, ſeeing I was well and in good health every way at the end of the time, which thing was ſo taken notice of (amongſt them) that they could not endure to detain us longer after, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Lord making way for us, we were releaſed, and we took our journey towards <hi>France,</hi> where, in the Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God, I was drawn forth to warn both Rulers, Prieſts, and People (in Town, City, and Country) until I came through the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and being ready to take ſhipping for <hi>England,</hi> I ſpake unto two Prieſts of the Popiſh Order, unto whom I declared (as I had done unto many more) deſtruction and a final end of all Idol Prieſts, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, and Idolaters, for which Cauſe I violently was halled away and committed to priſon, in a Court called <hi>Bucke De Ault,</hi> which was between <hi>Deap</hi> and <hi>Abbuilly,</hi> about <hi>20</hi> Leagues from <hi>Dover,</hi> where I continued about the ſpace of <hi>2</hi> Moneths; and after publick Examination and Tryall, the Priſon doores were ſet open, from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55273:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>whence I paſſed to <hi>Callis,</hi> continuing ſtill to warn the People, for which Cauſe I was had before the Magiſtrates, and being exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them, they let me paſs away toward <hi>Graveling,</hi> where I was at the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nunnery, where I warned them, though they would not let me ſee their face; and after ſome threatning I had from their Priest, I departed from thence toward <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where I was preſently taken up (by the Governour's Officers) and by him retained as Priſoner in his own houſe until the next day he ſent me away in a Friggot of the Kings for <hi>England,</hi> alleadging for his ſo doing, that it was becauſe he feared I would make a diſturbance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Papiſts, ſaying to this purpoſe, that there was Articles of agreement betwixt them, and that they were not to be diſturbed, which thing he feared I would do; and I being landed at <hi>Deale,</hi> I paſſed towards <hi>Dover,</hi> to viſit my friends after this my ſore tryal and travel amongſt the Papiſts, and e're I was in that Town <hi>24</hi> houres, I was by the Mayor of the Town taken from a friends houſe of mine, and committed to priſon, for a Jeſuite, where I remained about <hi>7</hi> Moneths; and after my releaſe from thence, I took my journey towards <hi>London,</hi> where I had not been long, but I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the Magiſtrates of the City as they were ſitting at a Court in the <hi>Old Bayly,</hi> who eſpied me only as a beholder of other tranſactions against my Dear friends (who are called <hi>Quakers</hi>) for which they ſent for me and tendred me the Oath, making that the ſame ſnare to enſnare me, as their manner was and is ſtill to doe to the innocent; and from thence I was Committed to <hi>New-gate,</hi> where I was with many more of my Brethren kept about the ſpace of <hi>4</hi> Moneths, until I was ſo weak, that I was carried out in a Chaire: And upon my recovery from this weakneſſe, I went unto one of our publick Meeting-places (neare <hi>Alderſ-gate</hi> in <hi>London</hi>) where I was taken again, with the Lords innocent People, under the pretence of Plotters, which thing we were wholly cleere of, for the thing then intended or pretended againſt us, was a plot, which was afterwards found to be intended by a people contrary-minded unto us, both in their lives, practiſes, and principles, for which ſome of them ſuffered death, who were wholly ſtrangers unto us, and woe unto ſuch kind of plotters? Notwithſtanding, many of us ſuffered im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment until death, in, and about <hi>London</hi> for this Cauſe, amongſt whom I was a deep ſufferer, until the laſt, though the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55273:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>did confeſſe to mine and our innocency. And all this, as for mine own particular, I could have buried in oblivion, and never have made mention of it more, were it not for the cleering of the innocency of that Truth of God, which I profeſſe and live in, from the ſcandalous reproaches of <hi>Iſhmael's</hi> ſtock, at whoſe hands I have ſuffered ſuch things, as would be both long and hard to utter, it now being the ſixth time I have been committed to Priſon by the hands of unreaſonable men (ſince I have returned from <hi>Rome</hi>); once at <hi>Dover,</hi> and four times at <hi>London:</hi> All which ſufferings &amp; impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nothing was, or ever could be proved againſt me, as the breach of any Law, ſave that by which mens Conſciences are reſtrained from worſhipping of God, according to the perſwaſion of his Spirit (in their own Conſciences), and alſo becauſe I would not break Chriſts Commands, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, to obey the Commands of men</hi> (to ſwear): And though for thoſe two things I have ſo ſuffered, I have this day a Conſcience void of offence towards all men, who are of honeſt hearts, and am cleer alſo in the ſight of God concerning them both, and am at this inſtant Juſtified in his ſight; and he knoweth how that I ſeek the good of all men, though an open enemy to all deceitful works, hireling Prieſts, and Deceivers, upon the face of the Earth, whether in Pope or Prelate, or what ſort, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, or denomination ſoever.</p>
            <p>I had not been <hi>3</hi> Weekes releaſed out of <hi>London</hi> Priſon of <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> before I was committed here: In which Priſon I was committed by <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> only for ſpeaking a few words in the ſtreet, becauſe they did hinder me and my friends of going into our hired houſe, I being committed to the <hi>Counter</hi> but the Week before, for the ſame Cauſe, and releaſed about the middle of the week by <hi>Robinſon,</hi> then Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> and but <hi>3</hi> dayes before that, I was releaſed out of <hi>New-gate</hi> upon the death of Deare <hi>E. B.</hi> with whom I was a priſoner ſeverall Moneths (as both in one Priſon) though not in one Roome, but a little time before his death, in which the Lord did Everlaſtingly Crown him with Glory, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and bleſſing: For this I ſhall leave upon record concerning him, that as he was honourable in his life, ſo he was in death, and his ſeed ſhall praiſe his noble Acts for ever, in which he was Renowned.</p>
            <p>And now upon my releaſe in <hi>London,</hi> I tooke my journey towards
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55273:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>this City, where I had been but a ſhort time, to the number of two or three dayes, before I was caſt in Bonds here, only for ſpeaking to two Prieſts of this City, telling them the blind led the blind, and both would fall into the ditch; and as it happened one of them was blind, which was more than I know, for I had never ſeen their faces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but theſe men being guilty inwardly of the Charge, ſoone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it by their fruits and actions, who preſently cauſed me by reaſon of their complaints, to be had before their Rulers, who being willing and ready to ſatisfie their malicious deſires, did ſoon tender me the Oath, as there being not any ſeeming just cauſe in the other to cast me into Priſon, where I am at preſent a ſufferer in the patience and good will of God.</p>
            <p>And thus with as much brevity as I could, have I declared ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the hard meaſure which I have ſuſtained and received at the hands of unreaſonable men (in, and about <hi>3</hi> yeares time ſince I Landed at this City), upon my return from <hi>Virginia,</hi> after my ſore Captivity there; and truely had it not been by reaſon of the many and various reports which are concerning me (amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny), I know I ſhould have been ſtill willing to have concealed the grief of all this within my own bowels, yea, and notwithſtanding all theſe things (beſides the Lord alone, which might have induced me to this matter) I ſhould certainly have concealed it. And now after all this, in which, &amp; through which the Lord hath tryed my poor ſoul by the common enemy, if he ſhould try me at or by the hands of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends, as <hi>Job</hi> was, ſhall I be angry with him, or repine at it? God forbid; in whoſe good will I reſt, until he ariſe and plead my Cauſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Bayly.</signed> 
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Newgate</hi> Priſon in <hi>Briſtol</hi> 
                  <date>the 13 of the 3 Moneth, 1663</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="memoir">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55273:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A true and faithfull Relation of ſome of the ſufferings, tryals, ſorrows, and travels of the Seed and Spirit of God for the creature, and now of the creature, in with the ſame Seed and Spirit (manifeſt through an earthen veſſel) known by name <hi>C.B.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SUrely had I the Tongue of the Eloquent, and the Pen of a ready Writer, it would be hard for me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the grievouſneſs of my hard travels and ſorrow, which I have undergone, ſince I was but 12 or 13 years of Age, in which time my deep travell and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row began; it being ſo that in my tender years I had been tenderly brought up (about the Court of <hi>England</hi>), my natural Parents belonging thereunto, who were <hi>Roman</hi> Catholiques, in which Religion they carefully brought me up, ſparing neither coſt nor pains, for any thing which might tend unto my edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and bringing me up in that way: But my God intending to make me an inſtrument in his hand, for his own work, did raiſe up ſomething in my ſoul (of a child) which was of himſelf, which cauſed a ſecret diſlike (in my heart) of that Idolatrous way of worſhip, in ſo much that I could never heartily embrace the ſame; which thing hath cauſed tears to be ſhed for me (by my own friends, then, who dearly and tenderly loved me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto the love as Parents bear unto their Children;) and it being ſo, it raiſed a great diſcontent ſometimes in them to ariſe towards me, which was the firſt ground and original cauſe of my ſorrow, though I did not know what that was in my ſelf, which cauſed me for to diſlike it, both in way and worſhip, which ſince I found to be the light and gift of Gods grace in my ſoul, which was nigh me, and in me, at all times, and places, a ſure and living Witneſſe againſt all ſin and evill whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55273:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And from that time forwards, I was ever ſeeking for to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate my ſelf from my natural Parents; and the wars coming on in <hi>England,</hi> did enlarge my opportunity, for to fulfill my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended purpoſe, it being ſo that moſt of the Court Officers were diſmiſſed of their outward beings (in and about <hi>London,</hi>) where I had my natural birth and bringing up, untill about the Age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; and it being ſo, I did begin to wander about, not being kept at School, nor at Board, as formerly I had been: But my Parents being willing to have me to their own natural Countrey (which was <hi>France,</hi>) I paſſed thither with one who was Extraordinary Embaſſador ſent from the King of <hi>France</hi> (called the Prince <hi>Deicourt,</hi>) who loved me, and kept me by him ſome time for his Interpreter, whileſt he was in <hi>England;</hi> but ſtill ſomething there was in me, which could not be ſatisfied to feed at the Table of Princes, nor to be in their love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (without the love and favour of God), which made me ſtill in a reſtleſſe condition, which cauſed me for to return out of <hi>France,</hi> without the conſent and knowledge of my outward friends, or relations: And coming to <hi>England,</hi> at <hi>Graves-end,</hi> as I was intending to paſſe for <hi>London,</hi> I met with one <hi>Brad-ſtreet,</hi> who was commonly called a <hi>Spirit,</hi> for he was one of thoſe who did entice Children and People away for <hi>Virginia;</hi> he fell into diſcourſe with me, and I being tender in years, he did cunningly get me on Board of a Ship, which was then there riding ready for to go to thoſe parts, and I being once on Board, could never get on Shoar, untill I came to <hi>America,</hi> where I was ſold as a bond-ſlave for ſeaven years, in which time it would be too hard for me to ſhew (in every particular) the hardſhip and miſery that I did undergo (in that time of hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, cold, and nakedneſſe, beatings, whippings, and the like;) for many times was I ſtripped naked, and tied up by the hand, and whipped; and made to go bare-foot, and bare-legged in cold and froſty weather, and hardly cloaths to cover my naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beſides the ſoare and grievous labour which I was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually kept at, during which time my poor ſoul would be often bemoaning it ſelf (every way) concerning my ſoar captivity and miſery; and ſomething I can indeed ſay did in ſecret an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55273:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and refreſh my tender ſoul; in the feeling of which, I could in truth of heart ſay, I did forgive my then perſecutors: And when grief would be ready to ſwallow me up, I would conſider how that that which did then befall me, was ſurely for my good; and would rather judge my ſelf than others, beleeving that I indeed did deſerve it, and much more for my diſobedience, though of a truth it was very grievous and hard for me to beat, as to the very natural, what I did, and ſurely had not the ſecret hand of Gods love upheld me, I could never have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported my burden, there being ſuch an alteration with me, when I came to eat my bread in the Aſh heap, whenas before I had been in the preſence of Princes; and alſo the alteration both of food and every thing elſe; for inſtead of a well ſtringed Lute in my hand, I had hard labour, and my daily exerci e was beyond the common manner of Slaves, for mine was often night and day: I ſay, had it not been the very hand and love of God which had ſupported me, my very outward man would have been laid in the duſt, as ſeveral of my then fellow Labourers were, in a moſt ſad and deplorable condition, which thing I deſire may not be laid to their charge, who were the Authors of it; I ſay, the Lord forgive them for that which they did to them and me, for I am ſure the poor creatures had better have been hanged, than to have ſuffered the death and miſery they did; which thing I ſhould not in this place have ſpoken, were it not ſo, but that ſome of theſe Papers might come to the hands of thoſe who may in like manner be inflictors of ſuch miſery upon others, that ſo if there be but any remorſe, or place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance left in them, that they may yet repent of their evill, for it is very great; for though the man whom I ſerved was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and received a Member of an Independant Church, in thoſe parts, yet he was unconverted, as to the Lord; which ſhewed their light and diſcerning but little worth; for indeed, I never ſaw any change or alteration in the man at all. But I ſhall return unto the thing intended by me, which is to ſpeak of the goodneſſe and love of God unto my ſoul, that ſo all thoſe who might be like-minded with me, might not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair in any condition whatſoever they may fall into; if they do but love and fear the Lord, he will bring them out of the ſixth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55273:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>trouble, and alſo the ſeaventh in the end: For when I was out or this hard ſervitude, I could not for all that return to, or own that dark and deviliſh worſhip, whatever did become of me; for then I was come to a riper underſtanding, and growth, both in years and knowledge, in which I ſaw and confeſſed unto a hand of Divine Juſtice againſt that people, and alſo to a hand of Divine providence in bringing me there, where I heard and underſtood both outward and inward, that the Sword of the Lord was drawn againſt the wicked, in this Nation of <hi>England;</hi> and alſo I did obſerve in that day, how that the Parliament party did, and would moſt of all prevail, becauſe that there was ſomething raiſed up in them, againſt the groſſe Popery and Idolatry, and wickedneſſe which was then on ſoot in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which thing was the cauſe I did indeed moſtly affect them then, beyond any other people, though they were called Puritans in deriſion. But in a ſhort time the chiefeſt of thoſe people, who were amongſt us, loſt their firſt integrity, ſoon eſpecially, when the Lords hand had given their Brethren great reſt and victory from their enemies, and ſo ſoon turned that little liberty they had gotten to a wrong end, and made uſe of it as an occaſion to the fleſh, by which means they became as much in bondage as ever, every one ſeeking his own, and not anothers good; which thing I did in that day obſerve, though few knew that it was ſo with me, but outwardly I did in that day frequent, and indeed loved thoſe moſt who were the moſt honeſt amongſt men: But it being ſo in the main, that nothing but rioting, drinking, ſinging, and dancing was amongſt the beſt of men, I knew not what to do, but to be one of them, which I judged better of the two, than to return unto the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſtuff, for my very ſoul did abhor it; therefore I did rather chooſe to labour with my hands, and ſo get my bread with pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, than to return or make my ſelf known unto my neareſt relations any way, for I ſaid in my heart, their ſorrow is over concerning me. But in the midſt of all this, my ſoul in ſecret did mourn after a holy life of love, but could not ſee it born up in any living, amongſt whom I did converſe, or had any thing to do with. And as in relation to my own condition, I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55273:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>did often lament it, in ſecret, and would often ſay unto the Lord, Haſt thou created me thus to deſtroy me? for I ſaw how that I was ſtill ingrievous bondage unto ſin, and lead thereunto at the Devils will, and I felt in my ſelf how that the wages of ſin was death, becauſe of the terrours of the Lord that came upon my ſoul, by the reaſon of it, and whileſt that I was in this ſtate, my grief was more than could be uttered, or indeed ſeen by any; for I would often ſeem to do away ſorrow with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lightneſſe and vanity; yet ſtill in the very midſt of all this, I continued ſeeking in my heart a man of love, or a people in whom one might put confidence, which thing I was drawn unto, (by the good, which was of God in my own heart;) and as God did raiſe it me, ſo in the end he did anſwer it to me outwardly, by ſending one of his dear ſervants into thoſe parts, whoſe name was <hi>Elizabeth Harris,</hi> who ſoon anſwered that which was breathing after God in me; by which means I came with many more, to be informed in the way and truth of God, having a ſeal in my heart and ſoul of the truth of her meſſage, which indeed I had long waited for: And then when I had found this beloved life and people, I was like a man over-joyed in my heart; not onely becauſe that I heard that God had raiſed up ſuch a people in <hi>England,</hi> but alſo becauſe I ſaw the ſudden fruits and effects of it, both in my own heart, and in others, inſomuch that in a ſhort time we became all to be as one entire family of love, and were drawn together in his life, (which was his light in us) to wait upon him in the ſtill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and quietneſſe of our ſpirits, like ſo many people which deſired nothing but the pure teachings of Gods Spirit, in which we were often refreſhed together, and one in another: And when this I had found, and clearly underſtood, how that that which judged me, and condemned my ſoul for ſin, from my youth up untill that day, I ſay, when I came to ſee that this was the very way to God, I was as a man that had found that which his ſoul loved; and then had I had ten thouſand Crowns, I could have laid them all down at the feet of them, who then went forth to declare ſuch good and glad tidings of peace, and good-will, which was freely extended unto all the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55273:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sons of men; then happy man was I, if that I could but have ſerved, or have been any way ſerviceable unto ſuch of thoſe who went forth to declare, who were miniſtring ſervants in the hand of the Lord to us, whoſe pure life I loved and honoured in them above all; and then I was not onely made willing to have forſaken father, or mother, and all outward Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and favour of men, but alſo to have laid down my life for the Lords ſake; ſuch was the love that was raiſed in me, that I had rather have been a Priſoner with the deepeſt ſufferer in the greateſt ſorrow, and counted it more happineſſe ſo to be, than with the Princes of this world in their greateſt joy and dignity: And this was of the Lords own begetting in me, though few ſaw it then. And this I can tell thee Reader (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art) by true experience, that if thou find but ſuch a thing in thee, which bringeth a remorſe upon thee by reaſon of ſin, and draweth thy heart into tenderneſſe and pitty unto the oppreſſion and captivity which is upon all creatures, which they lye under by reaſon of ſin, in which, and by which men are degenerated from God; I ſay, that if thou find and feel but ſuch a thing in thee, prize it above all, for it is of the very life and reſtorer of all things, by which <hi>Moſes</hi> was acted in the dayes of old, when he did forſake the pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon, and choſe rather to partake of the ſuffering and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the afflicted, than to be called the ſon of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter; for it was that in which he wrought the wonders of God, and will alſo do the like in thee, if thou obey love and follow it, it will be thy guide, leader, and preſerver, and teacher, in all ſtates and conditions whatſoever, through which, and in which thy immortal ſoul will come to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſo ſatisfied; for I will tell thee plainly, that except man comes to be acquainted with ſomething in himſelf, which is more glorious than all viſible and tranſitory things without him, he can never come to forſake all for the Lords ſake: For this I have ſeen and experienced through deep travail and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, how that if I had not had ſomething in my own ſelf, which was more deſireable and amiable than all things, I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been made willing to have forſaken all things elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55273:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>it; but enjoying the life and preſence of my Creator, in my own particular, all was well enough without me, though in hunger, in cold, and in nakedneſſe, or priſons, or banniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or travails, both by Sea or Land, I did ſtill find ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and refreſhment in the enjoyment of Gods preſence; and this I ſay not becauſe another hath ſaid it, but becauſe my ſoul hath found it ſo in the time of need, even ſince the time that my God ſeparated me outwardly from my Brethren in <hi>Virginia,</hi> who were more neer and dear to me than all my outward kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe they were ſuch as did the will of my father; ſince which time ſomething of my travail may be ſeen in my follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, very briefly of my travels outward, but of my travels and ſorrow inward, in all thoſe travels and priſons, I ſhall leave it to the upright in heart to feel; for truly I may in the truth of God ſay, how that the dayes of my ſorrow and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, paſſed the number of my remembrance: Beſides the many aſſaults which the curſed Popiſh ſpirit of Inchantments, Sorcery, Witchcraft, did make againſt me, to deſtroy me, cannot be given to be underſtood by Tongue, Pen, Ink, nor Paper, but by thoſe who have undergone the like tryal with me; for this I teſtifie in the Lord, and ſhall leave upon record, under my hand, how that a deeper ſpirit of Necromancy and deceit, is not upon the face of the whole earth to be found, ſo deep in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the miſtery of iniquity, as it is amongſt them; and this is the teſtimony which I give for the Lord God of life againſt them, which ſhall ſtand for ever. For as to my very outward, they have ſought my death and deſtruction by this means; and I have been almoſt ſtrangled in the night and day ſeaſon, by that curſed ſpirit of Witchcraft, which hath ſought to ſtop my mouth, thereby to have deprived me of my natural breath, which thing they would certainly have done, had not the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me, and rebuked them; for they have often come into my Priſon, with many hundred ſorts of ſhapes and likeneſſes, and have ſought every way of Inchantment againſt me, and had it been ſo, that it had been poſſible for them to have proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt me, to the utter deſtruction of me; they would have done it; but when the Lord had ſuffered them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55273:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>every way to try me, then he wholly rebuked them, and ſent his miniſtring Angels to comfort me every way, as thoſe poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning ſpirits had every way aſſaulted me; in which day of his everlaſting love, he ſealed up my ſoul in his everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of love for ever, for which cauſe I cannot forſake the Lord, whatever betides me. Now though tryals remain yet on every hand, yet my God knoweth I can never leave him, nor forſake him, nor decline from his living teſtimony in my heart, neither in life, nor death, but muſt and ſhall ſay unto all, love, fear, dread, and honour, and obey the Lord above all, who is worthy to have for ever, all the glory, honour, and praiſe, even him who is God over all, bleſſed for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the end why my God ſeparated me from my fathers houſe, in the time of my infancy, that I ſhould be a true and faithfull witneſſe againſt that ſpirit of perſecution, murder, and envy, in whomſoever it be. And ſeeing the Lord hath thus long preſerved me out of many eminent dangers, I know he will do the like for ever, as he hath ſpoken it unto my ſoul, that he will never ſuffer his faithfulneſs to fail concerning me; therefore I ſhall never be moved; and if it were not ſo, my ſoul would long ere now have ſunk under the floods of deep ſorrow, which yet come upon me without ceaſing, rowling over my head; the Lord rebuke them, as I know he will do, for his name ſake, even he who hath heard me out of the Whales belly, and anſwered my requeſt once and again in the day of need, for which, I ſay, my ſoul magnifie, bleſſe, and praiſe his holy name for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Bayly.</signed> 
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Newgate</hi> Priſon in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                  <date>the firſt of the third Month. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:55273:9"/>
            <p>AND now the Magiſtrates of this Nation (through whoſe hands I have paſſed thus from Priſon to Priſon) may ſee what they have done, if it be ſo they are not yet quite heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind, in the perſecuting of a man ſo unreaſonably as they have done, who hath been ſo far drawn forth as in relation to the very natural part, as to render his life and body for one of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Countrey men, who had been in long captivity in <hi>Rome,</hi> out of their Nation (even one, who was not himſelf a natural <hi>Engliſh</hi> man) though born in it; I ſay, ſurely following Generations might well ſay, the Heathen in <hi>America</hi> would not have thus rewarded a man, upon the return of ſuch a ſervice as this done for any one of their Nation, I am ſure they would not have done it: And what right can any man expect to have at, or of the hands of ſuch men, who are thus lead by a ſpirit of wrong judgement, as for to perſecute in ſuch a nature their friend, in the ſtead of their enemy, eſpecially ſuch a man as hath in this ſort jeoparded his life, to witneſſe againſt the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Religion, and not onely ſo, but hath undergone all and much more than the aforeſaid miſeries, rather than to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and own it. Of theſe things, and concerning theſe things, I ſhall in the uprightneſſe of my heart, leave it and commit it unto God, the judge of all, for to judge of this matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="warning">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55273:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A true and faithfull Warning unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Briſtol;</hi> as a loving viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods tender love unto them, that thereby they may take warning, and turn from the evill of their wayes, and repent with ſpeed.</head>
            <p>FOr the Sword of the Lord is already drawn over the City, and is made ready for the ſhedding of much blood, and for hewing of the mighty in pieces. And this is the Word of the Lord unto you all, both Rulers, Prieſts, and People, of what ſort or degree ſoever; and if it were ſo, that <hi>Abraham, Lot, Job,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> were in the City, yet ſhould not they deliver it from the fierce ſtroak of the Almighty, which is ready to come upon it by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſin and tranſgreſſion, ſo much the more, ſaith the Lord God of vengeance, becauſe my glorious truth hath been ſo much declared in it, above and beyond any other of its neighbouring places; for thus ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts, the mighty and terrible one, <hi>If the mighty works had been done in Sodom and Gomorrah, which have been done in thee, O Briſtot, they might ſurely have repented.</hi> But ye have ſurely ſlighted it, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it as a thing of nought; you are even fled as it were upon Horſes into your dark <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, and reliques of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and confuſion, and there as it were ſetled your ſelves upon the old lees of Popery, which my hand is ſtretched out againſt, and ſhall never more be with-drawn, untill I have cut off, and quite rooted it out of all Nations, both root and branch; and they who go about to hold it up, or any part or parcel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſuch ſhall be the object of my fierce anger, that both them and it ſhall ſurely fall together, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. And foraſmuch as ye do with out-ſtretched necks, reſiſt my truth, and ſay in your heart, we will not that this thing rule over us;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55273:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore ſhall the ſword of my anger bring you down, if you continue ſtill in your gainſayings againſt me; and whatever is high and exalted in this City, ſhall be bowed down; the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe, who will not that any thing reign but his ſon alone, whom all the Angels muſt worſhip, and every knee be made to bow, and every tongue to confeſſe unto him for ever, and own his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgements, which ſhall come upon the high, lofty, and proud, and rebellious, who forget God.</p>
            <p>Therefore haſte, haſte, haſte, with ſpeed, and repent, and remember <hi>Nineveh,</hi> who repented at the preaching of <hi>Jonas;</hi> and a greater than <hi>Jonas</hi> is here, and hath been here in many Prophets, to warn thee, and as ſure as God lives, if ye take not warning hereby, and repent, ye ſhall ſhortly know, unto your ſorrow, that a Prophet hath been amongſt you ſent of the Lord, who ſought not yours but you, that your immortal ſouls might come to be ſaved from the wrath, tribulation, and anguiſh, which is ready to come down from the righteous Judge of all, upon you.</p>
            <p>O People Conſider whileſt you have time, what a ſad deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing will it be, when ye ſhall be likened to a generation of Vipers and dead Adders, ſaying, <hi>We have piped unto you, and yet have not danced, we have mourned unto you, and you have no lamented;</hi> as thoſe who would <hi>not hearken to the voyce of the Charmer, though he charms never ſo wiſely:</hi> For aſſuredly, if ye ſtill ſlight Gods tender viſitation of love unto you, many may take up a lamentation for you, but none will be able to help you: As the Lamb of God, who came to lay down his life for the ſins of the whole world; yet becauſe his love was rejected, ſlighted, and not received; the day came that he took up a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation over that place, people and City, which he would have gathered up into his armes of love, whoſe tender bowels of pity and compaſſion, was moved for them, ſaying, <hi>O Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Jeruſalem, how often would I have gathered thee, as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings, and ye would not.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had ſlighted the day of ſmall things, and would have none of his reproofs; therefore was the things which belonged
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55273:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>to their everlaſting peace hid from their eyes: So likewiſe will it be with you, oh Inhabitants of <hi>Briſtol;</hi> many in thee whoſe loves are unfained in the lowly life of the Lamb, and deſired nothing but thy everlaſting peace and welfare; ſuch I ſay in like manner will come to take up a Lamentation in thee, and for thee, ſaying, Oh fooliſh and unwiſe people, had you but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the things which belonged to your everlaſting peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came thus to be hid from your eyes, ſurely ye would have been a bleſſed people for ever; but now inſtead of it, weeping and howling will for ever be your portion. Oh people for ever conſider this thing before it come upon you, whilſt yet the door of mercy is ſet open for you, and a hand freely ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth out of the tender boſom of God, to gather you up into his boſome, which is ready open to receive you; but if ye refuſe his loving kindneſs and his mercies, then hell fire will open her mouth wide for you, into which you will all be caſt with all the workers of iniquity, there to be tormented with the Devill and his Angels for evermore: And this will be your portion on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the hand; if ye cleave unto the good which God by his Son hath placed by his own Light in your hearts, then everlaſtingly happy will ye be, and all thoſe who come to witneſſe an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Saints in light:</p>
            <p>But if you hate the good, and love the evill, which the Prince of darkneſs hath put in you, then ye chooſe unto your ſelves death inſtead of life, and the Prince of the power of the Air will be your God and King, inſtead of the Prince of peace, and ſo ſad and lamentable will be your condition, who have had as much, if not more of the loving Viſitation of Gods love in his dear and precious Servants, than any people or Nation whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; for have ye not had <hi>line upon line, and precept upon precept?</hi> the Lord ſending his Prophets riſing up early; yea it might be ſaid early, foraſmuch that the Lords love reached unto you, as it were in the very morning and breaking forth of his glorious Sun of righteouſneſs, after this long and dark woful night of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and confuſion, which hath over-ſhadowed all Nations and people of the earth, which ſhall never ſet more until it hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpelled all the darkneſs forevermore never to riſe; and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55273:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet ſtill, and yet for all this you yet remain in your ſins, even you who are again turned to your old hireling Prieſts, which the Land had as it were vomited up long agoe, becauſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs; for in ſimplicity of heart conſider, were not they unprofitable unto you, and all people over whom they were? and did they not find you in your ſins, and did they not leave you there? and now upon their return have they not found you the ſame ſtill? And what think you of this? is it not high time for you to be awakened and look about you, ſeeing the day is ſo far ſpent of your lives, and you know not how ſoon the Lord may call for your breath out of your noſtrils? and what can ye in righteouſneſs think will become of you, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>As the Tree falls, ſo it lyes:</hi> and <hi>There is no Repentance in the Grave:</hi> and <hi>If ye dye in your ſins, where I go ye cannot come,</hi> ſaith Chriſt? And if ye do but confeſs him to be a man of truth, and theſe ſayings true, then ye may ſoon paſſe the ſentence of eternal condemnation in your ſelves, ſeeing that tribulation and anguiſh is to come upon every ſoul of man that doth evil, even to <hi>Jew</hi> as well as <hi>Gentile.</hi> And the Apoſtle in plain words, without wreſting, ſaith, <hi>Nothing that worketh abomination, or maketh a lye, muſt enter into the holy City.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let no man deceive you with vain words, for ſuch as ye ſow, ſuch ſhall ye reap.</hi> Now ſee if your Prieſts be not the very men, who are deceiving you with vain words, who tell you that you can never be freed from ſin, yet ſay, it ſhall go well with you. They call you good Chriſtians, though ye do bring forth the Devils work: Or which of you in or amongſt you, will deny to partake of that which they call <hi>the Seal of the Covenant,</hi> though they are never ſo wicked and ungodly in all their words and actions: Surely, ſurely, the Lord is highly diſpleaſed with theſe things. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this Warning ſent amongſt you that you may come away from ſuch a deviliſh Prieſthood, as preacheth up ſin unto you for tearm of life, that is till ye can ſin no longer: Surely, they <hi>who made a Covenant with Hell and Death</hi> in the dayes of old, were never more lead into the <hi>Myſterie of iniquity,</hi> than theſe.</p>
            <p>And thus the Devil hath his Kingdome by conſent both of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55273:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prieſts and people. Oh, horrid wickedneſs is this, that ever men ſhould thus ſell themſelves unto the Devil for diſhoneſt gain, and filthy lucres ſake, to preach up ſin unto people; theſe are they who trample upon the Blood of the Covenant, and ſay in effect that its uneffectual and unſufficient to purge the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from all ſin and uncleanneſſe; but ſuch, people, ye muſt ceaſe from; for they who were real and true Miniſters of Chriſt, ſaid, <hi>The wages of ſin is death,</hi> therefore laboured to bring peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therefrom; whoſe Miniſtry was powerful and effectual enough in that work to accompliſh the ſame: For <hi>Paul</hi> when he writ to the <hi>Romans,</hi> amongſt whom he had laboured <hi>to turn them from darkneſſe to light,</hi> and ſuch came to be <hi>turned from Satans power to Gods,</hi> by whoſe power they came to be redeemed and made free from ſin, and ſo became Gods children: And this was the fruits and effects of thoſe who were ſent of God, and were not hirelings, <hi>for ſuch run and are not ſent;</hi> therefore, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>they profit not the people at all,</hi> no more than yours do now; for I ſay, as you love and prize the ſalvation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of your immortal ſouls, conſider theſe things: Is the wicked man returned from his naughtineſſe amongſt you? is not a Lyar a Lyar ſtill, a Swearer a Swearer ſtill, and ſo likewiſe all others whatſoever? And if any ſhould go to your Prieſts to be eaſed of his burden, which come upon him by reaſon of ſin, what eaſe can he have ſeeing his Prieſt is a ſinner as well as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if not a worſe, and in effect will tell him he cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin while he is in the body of fleſh; and ſo by this means, as you were born and conceived in ſin, ſo ye live, and ſo ye dye. And this is the fruits of your Miniſtry, and yet you have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the reading of the Scriptures, which ſaith and ſheweth how that <hi>the true Chriſtians are to be redeemed from their vain converſations,</hi> and did witneſſe a purging and redemption there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, <hi>not with the blood of Bulls and Goats, but with the Blood of the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſins of the World:</hi> Mark that, people, and ſee if ye are not wholly ſtrangers to this thing, and to the very end and coming of Chriſt, who was made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in fleſh, to the end that the righteouſneſſe of the Law might be fulfilled in all thoſe <hi>who walk not after the fleſh, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55273:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>after the Spirit,</hi> and to ſuch there is no condemnation: But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you who are following your blind guides, and are ſtrangers unto this thing, condemnation from the righteous God the Judg of all, will for evermore be ſeated upon your heads, except ye repent, even on you who are ſtrangers unto the Spirit of God, and are walking in the fleſh, and are fulfilling the luſts thereof, and are reſolved ſo to do until your dying day; in which thing I warn you to repent in Gods pure power and dread, and turn unto the Lord God by forſaking the evil of your wayes; which if you do not, as ſure as God hath ſet <hi>Sodom</hi> for an example of his eternal wrath and Judgment, ſo ſure will this come upon you if you ſlight this the day of your viſitation, which is now over your heads, I ſay, repent before it fall upon you, and the night overtake you, in which no man can work. And this is a true and faithfull warning unto you all from the Lord God of love, who deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but that he would turn from his evil wayes and live; and if you do this, then bleſſed will you be for ever, but if ye refuſe, then will you be left without excuſe, and I ſhall be clear of your blood before the Lord, who required this of me to do, and to ſay unto you; which in faithfulneſs I have done without reſpect unto perſons, time or place, as the free Spirit of God hath given me utterance thereunto, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hatred or diſſimulation at all: Therefore live or dye, my peace is and will be with the Lord for ever.</p>
            <p>And now if any ſhould ſay amongſt you, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> Why unto ſuch I ſay in the tender bowels of Gods love, turn unto the Light of Gods own ſon, which ſhineth in your dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, even in your dark hearts, and receive it, love it, follow it, and obey it with all your ſoul, with all your mind, and with all your ſtrength, and then <hi>power will be miniſtred unto you, whereby ye will become the Sons of God, and to be born of him, which birth ſinneth not;</hi> but in it there is power over the man of ſin, which hath born rule in the firſt birth, which was according to the fleſh, in which none can pleaſe God, foraſmuch as it luſteth againſt the Spirit continually, and will do until it be wholly crucified with the luſts and affections thereof: If ye come to receive the Gift of Gods Grace and Spirit in your own hearts, a meaſure of which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55273:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>is given every one to profit withall; walking in it, and dwelling in it, ye will come to be led into all truth, and will come to deny all that is of the Devil and his works; which is the other of your ſad ſtates and conditions, ever ſaying, as you are indeed, <hi>unprofitable ſervants, leaving undone thoſe things which you ought to have done, and doing thoſe things which you ought not to do;</hi> which is a ſtate far different from a true Chriſtian ſtate, even as far as light is from darkneſs; for the true Chriſtians they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Chriſt, heard his voyce, and kept his Commandments, becauſe they loved him, and not their own lives.</p>
            <p>And again, if any ſhould ſay, <hi>I would willingly do this, that my ſoul might be ſaved from eternal condemnation, which I do believe will come upon all thoſe who live in their ſins and dye in them; but alaſs I have not power to do it, I am overcome and accuſtomed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to evill.</hi> Unto ſuch in much tenderneſs of heart, I ſay, if thou love the Light, and take up thy daily croſſe therein, thou wilt aſſuredly find power given thee to do the Will of God, in the doing of which thy ſoul will come to be ſanctified, and thy body purified and made fit for the Maſters uſe, who will come in and live with thee, and make his abode there for ever; but if thou take not up the daily croſſe, thou canſt not be a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Chriſt, profeſſe what thou wilt.</p>
            <p>But then if thou ſhouldſt not mind the Light of Chriſt, which condemns thee for ſin, and hath ſo done from thy youth up, and ſhouldſt enter into the reaſoning part with fleſh and blood, and ſay, what muſt I now forſake all my worldly delights, and run the hazard alſo of forſaking my familiar friends, kinsfolks, and acquaintance, and all my Pariſh Prieſts, and be mocked and denyed of all? and ſuch like things as theſe I know will get into thy fleſhly mind, all which I ſhall in a few words and in ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of heart anſwer: And firſt, as concerning thy forſaking of all, which is manifeſt to be the very way and firſt ſtep onwards towards thy ſouls peace and reſt, for <hi>He that forſakes not all, and hates not all, even to the very life, he can never purchaſe unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the pearl which Chriſt ſpeaks of, which was hid in the field.</hi> And as for the worldly delights, thereby the innocent (which ſhould give thee life and ſtrength againſt ſin) comes to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55273:13"/>but as I ſaid, if the croſſe thou come to know, the world and its delights will come to be crucified unto thee, and thee unto it all, and ſo the Reſurrection of the Juſt will come to be witneſſed, which before in thee was crucified by reaſon of thy worldly delights, ſins, luſts and tranſgreſſions. And as for the forſaking of thy Pariſh Prieſts, it is high time for thee to forſake them, ſeeing that little profit thou haſt had by them; for if thou comeſt to the Law of God in thy own heart, then thou wilt come to know the Lord, who will teach thee to profit, and to walk in the way of peace and holineſſe, which the hireling Prieſts know not, ſeeing they ſay that <hi>men cannot live without ſin,</hi> and yet ſay, <hi>it ſhall go well with them,</hi> contrary unto the Prophet of God, who ſaid, <hi>There is no peace to the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, I ſay unto you all who in any meaſure deſire ſalvation to your immortal ſouls, &amp; to be diſentangled from the Devils ſnares, father and mother, houſe and land, wife and children, thou muſt not at all count loſſe; for if thou ſhouldſt looſe them for the Lords ſake, thou ſhalt come to receive an hundred-fold in this life, and in the world to come life everlaſting. And this will be the portion of all thoſe that follow the Lamb through many tribulations, into the everlaſting Kingdome, peace, joy, holineſſe, and reſt for ever; and ſuch know the vanity and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of your water-dippings of Infants, Bels, Organs, and Surplices, and ſuch fooliſh Popiſh Inventions, to be but the meer Cheats and Traditions of men; and alſo ſuch will come to know the true ſpiritual Faith, Hope, and Baptiſm of Chriſt, which waſheth, purgeth, and maketh clean the ſoul, and gives Victory over Sin, Hell, Death, and the Grave, and him to be the only Lord in all, and over all, bleſſed for ever, in God the Father and Fountain of all good, with a ſincere heart to be kept and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in God, the Life and Father of all good, who is bleſſed, feared and honoured of all who keep in the word of his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſit down in the Lambs Throne of life and comfort for ever, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given forth through a ſufferer for the truth of God in <hi>Newgate</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                  <date>the 30. of the 3. Month. 1663.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Charles Baily.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55273:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A ſeaſonable Word of Exhortation (by way of Advice) to all the National Prieſts (in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England),</hi> but moſt eſpecially to them in and of <hi>Briſtol;</hi> wherein their unjuſt proceedings and violence (under a pretence of Miniſtry of Chriſt) is ſharply reproved, yet in a mild and moderate frame and temper of ſpirit. Alſo, That they may come to a further tryal of their ſtanding, they are required to anſwer thoſe <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> following (to Magiſtrates and People.)</head>
            <p>YOU Prieſts of <hi>Briſtol</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> the word of the Lord is to you, and his Controverſie is againſt you, and the Rod of his anger ſhall bring you down; weeping and howling ſhall be heard in your Aſſemblies, and Satyrs ſhall poſſeſſe your High Places, and the skreeking of Night birds ſhall be heard there: Your Prayers and your Oaths are alike unto the Lord; and your Faſts and your Gluttony is all one in his ſight; ye cauſe the people to erre by your lyes, and by your lightneſſe; and following your ſteps, they are led into confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, who like a bird are taken in your crafty ſnares of deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: The word of the Lord you have not to preach to the people, but the conceptions of your own minds and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, gathered out of that which other men have ſaid; ſome of which was ſpoken by the Spirit of the Lord, and ſome is but the ill-ſhapen brats of your own minds, and of others who were of your own Generation, who ſtole the word from their neighbour, and then brought it forth in a confuſed mixture and wiſdome, all which you compound together, and mix with your own deceit, to fill up an hours talk with, and then like a company of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, ye come out into your publick Market-places, where (by the means of your inſtigations) moſt of the people are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55273:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>to come, and buy this your ware; and then you ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, <hi>Hear the word of the Lord,</hi> whereas ye, nor your hearers do not know him, but have in your vain imaginations limited him above the Skies, like an old man.— O ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and blaſphemers, the Lord will ariſe like a man of War, and bring you down, and will caſt you headlong into <hi>Tophet,</hi> where the breath of his noſtrils ſhall for ever kindle up the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire of your endleſſe torments, except ye repent with ſpeed; the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall ſurely and ſhortly come to paſſe, in a time and hour when you ſhall not be aware of it; for <hi>as the lightning comes from the Eaſt, and ſwiftly paſſeth unto the Weſt, ſo ſhall the day of your deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be, except you amend:</hi> Amend therefore, and ceaſe preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto others, until you come your ſelves to be converted, and changed from that corrupt curſed nature of wickedneſſe, which lodgeth within you. O ye hypocrites, are you not, or at leaſt may you not be aſham'd to get into a high place amongſt people, and ſpeak againſt ſin and iniquity, ſeeing you your ſelves are not purged from it? May not that ſaying be juſtly turned upon you, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, ſaying, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexcuſable art thou O man, whoſoever thou art, that judgeth,</hi> ſeeing that no man was to judg another, whilſt he himſelf was guilty of the ſame thing. O ye deceitful workers, firſt pluck out the beam out of your own eyes, and then may you come for to ſee the clearer in others conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Until then this is a ſure and certain warning unto you all, to ceaſe from the evil of your wayes, and repent; for as ſure as God lives, if you go on in your ſtiff-neckedneſſe, and hard-heartedneſſe againſt him, his righteous Judgments will aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overtake you. And this I have written as one that feareth the Lord, and trembleth at his word; in which I cannot reſpect the perſons of any, but muſt reprove the ſins of all, whether in Kings, Princes, Rulers, or Judges, Prieſts or people, (of what ſort or condition ſoever) that thereby they may take warning, and repent.</p>
            <p>O <hi>England, England,</hi> many have been thy Warnings, and precious have been thy Viſitations, to thoſe who have prized them; and glorious hath been the day of Gods love, unto thoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55273:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Who have believed our report, and to whom the Arm of the Lord hath been revealed;</hi> which hath led them out of darkneſſe into his marvelous light, therein to live and to walk ſafe, out of the ſnare of the crafty Fowler, hireling Prieſt, and deceivers, which thou, O <hi>England,</hi> haſt embraced as it were anew (after thy long day of blood, ſorrow, and anguiſh.) O conſider this, O ye Heads of the Nation; to what end and purpoſe did the Lord empty the power of this Nation, from veſſel to veſſel, and from man to man? was it, think ye, that it ſhould ſettle again in this bogg and reliques of confuſed Popery? nay, ſurely nay, this was not the end of the Lord concerning thee; but his end and purpoſe concerning thee, was and is, that the Son of his own boſome ſhould be raiſed over all (in thee to Reign) as he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and decreed, which decree is impoſſible to be altered or changed, but ſhall and muſt be accompliſhed, not only in this Nation, but over all Nations; and in all Nations and people of the earth, ſhall this his glorious work be compleatly finiſhed; for he hath ſworn by himſelf, ſaying, it ſhall be ſo, that <hi>he ſhall reign over all the Kingdomes of the world,</hi> foraſmuch as I have appointed him to be <hi>heir of all things, both in Heaven and Earth;</hi> They that have an ear, let them hear; and bleſſed will be that eye which ſeeth, and that heart which underſtandeth the things which belong to their everlaſting peace, before they be hid from their eyes, and there be no place found for their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall further ſay (in the Spirit of the Lord) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thee O <hi>England;</hi> what the Lord intended ſhould be thy lot, 'twas that thou ſhouldeſt be the firſt fruit unto God in this latter day, that ſo thou mightſt become a glorious example unto other Nations, giving light unto them who yet ſat in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in the Region and ſhadow of death, that ſuch, I ſay, might have received light from the glorious Sun of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which the Lord raiſed in the midſt of thee (in thouſands); and this the Lord hath already in meaſure done, <hi>Glory be to him for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! might not my ſoul take up a Lamentation over a fooliſh people, ſaying, O how are your hearts becom blind, O inhabitants
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55273:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>England?</hi> in whom the voyce of the Turtle is plentifully heard, as in the Spring time, after this dry long Winter, which hath been in thee (amongſt whom it is on every hand ſaid and confeſſed, that <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> who hath brought his Seed out of the North, and cauſed the beauty of its life to appear, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the glory and beauty of this preſent world): And plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully hath the word of his own life been declared, and is ſtill ſpoken forth in thee; and yet for all this, like an inchanted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ye turn your backs upon it, and fly unto your hireling Prieſts, whereas thou mightſt have received the word of the Lord plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully and freely, at the hands of his precious Servants; then wouldſt thou have no need of the teachings of men, nor to have gone into the Idol Maſſe-houſes, there to have taken the words of <hi>David</hi> and others, to have ſung; but in the Spirit of the Lord ye would have all been gathered by it, through which ye would have been ever praiſing the Lord (in the land of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing): Neither would you have needed to have gone to your Prieſts, to have taken bread and wine at their polluted hands, which feedeth but the natural, and will corrupt; but you would have been come to the High-Prieſt, and Shepherd of your ſouls, and have received living bread at his hands, as your daily food and nouriſhment. O <hi>England,</hi> might not well my ſoul ſay, that thou haſt changed beauty for aſhes, and haſt choſen chaff inſtead of wheat? ſo that <hi>inſtead of well ſet hair, thou haſt baldneſſe,</hi> for if it were not ſo, thou neededſt not to have gone to the Idol-houſes now, for to hear a compounded parcel of words, called <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> read by a wicked man; but inſtead thereof thou hadſt been filled with the Spirit of Prayer and Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Lord would have ſhowred down upon thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, which thing, ſome few, who are deſpiſed in thee, do witneſſe, to the everlaſting comfort of their immortal ſouls: And alſo thou mightſt have had a free Miniſtry, inſtead of hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; even you who might have fed on living bread at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord, inſtead of taking it at your Communion-Tables, which the Popes ordained for you; who might have been bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Holy Ghoſt, and with fire, by which ye would have been cleanſed; who might have walked in the light of the Lord,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55273:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>inſtead of walking in the dim ſparks of your own kindling; who might have been ſatisfied with Gods preſence, inſtead of being enquiring in your minds, where, and what God is; who might have been purged, waſhed and made clean from ſin by the blood of the Lamb, inſtead of a vain hope, as you are in now, that ye ſhall be freed, but you know not when; who might have come to have witneſſed your bodies to have been the Temples of God, inſtead of ſeeking, as ye do now, in the Temples made with hands. O ye fooliſh, and unwiſe people, what might my ſoul ſay unto you of theſe things? Ye have refuſed the teachings of God, and ſeek after the teachings of men; ye have ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the true Shepherd, <hi>who hath laid down his life for his Sheep,</hi> and have followed the falſe Shepherd, whoſe the Sheep are not, but an hireling he is, and fleeth (becauſe he is an hireling) when the wolfe and florm cometh.</p>
            <p>For hath not this been manifeſtly ſeen in thee, O <hi>England,</hi> that when the forcible powers of the Earth was for them, then they cryed, woe, woe unto us if we preach not the Goſpel; and we preach not for hire, as we are falſly accuſed (by theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Quakers,) but a neceſſity is on us, ſo to do, and if we had not any thing for ſo doing, yet we could not hold our peace; but ſeeing the Law of the Nation gives us yearly maintenance, we take it as our due; and though it be a Popiſh conſtitution, we take no notice of it, ſeeing the Property of the thing is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as being taken from them, who were no Miniſters of the Goſpel, and given unto us who are truly ſo, unto whom not onely the Tenths of all things belongeth, but all things ſhould be laid down at our feet, <hi>(as it was in the Primitive time);</hi> and this hath been the general cry of your Prieſts, unto whom you give ear, and not unto us who told you the truth in that day, as we do in this day, ſaying take away but their compelled main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ceaſe putting into their mouths, and they will ſoon prepare war againſt you, if the Powers of the earth will but help them, if not, then their God they will truſt no longer, and ſoon their neceſſity of preaching will be taken off them, and they will fly into their holes, like Dragons, wiſhing for another nights ſeaſon, that ſo they might come out upon their prey afreſh. And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55273:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this which is here ſaid, there is no wrong done unto them; your by-paſt Prieſts have themſelves by their words and actions, largely proved the truth of this matter.</p>
            <p>And now unto you Prieſts, unto whom I was made to ſpeak the word of the Lord, woe and miſery will aſſuredly be your Portion, if you ſlight Gods tender love unto your ſouls: For that which I now ſpeak, and that which I formerly ſpoke unto you, is not, God knows, in contempt, nor in any way to divide you, but in tender love to warn you from the evil of your ways, that ſo by turning from the evil, and cleaving to the good, ye may come to eſcape the dreadful Judgments of God, which are nigh to overtake you. And that you are, and were manifeſt to be ſuch as I ſaid you to be, is true, <hi>(to wit)</hi> That you were blind guides, leaders of the blind, inaſmuch as ye are hireling Prieſts made by the will of men, who forceth a people by a Law, for to take your ſtuff, which makes you worſe than a common hireling; who are far from being Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, called by him to his own work, for ſuch miniſter freely as they received freely of their Lord and Maſter. And ſo, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them;</hi> ſo do we know you, who have nothing you have, freely given, neither can you freely give; nay you have not ſo much as the Sheeps cloathing, but you are out wardly and inwardly ravened, and gone into the Wolfs nature (of tearing and devouring, and perſecuting, like the Pope, your chief head, and leader in this work); though ſome of you are ignorantly blind, yet many of you are wilfully blind, which will not ſerve your turns: Awake, awake, and conſider, do you think it ſhall ſerve any of your turns, to cry out againſt Popery in words, and in nature to be found all one, in Perſecution, Malice, and Envy? as one of you told me, <hi>I ſhould not have liberty to ſpeak</hi> (after he had accuſed me openly before the people); and the other of you told me, <hi>he did forgive me,</hi> after he had delivered me into the hands of men, and I was to be ſent to priſon: O ſhame will come upon you for theſe things, and the dreadful rod of Gods anger will overtake you for it. And tell me what you have at beſt to give to the people, (for your yearly maintenance which you have of them,) but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55273:17"/>what is already made ready to your hands of other mens lines, partly by the Pope and his Adherents, who ſteal the words of Apoſtles and holy men of God, and mix them with their own inventions; and this is made a plat-form for you to pray and preach by: and at the beſt this is your ſtuff, which you confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly force upon the people, to ſay and to ſpeak after you, for which they muſt give many hundred pounds unto you and your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of hirelings, even for this which profiteth them not at all, but people under your teachings live and die in their ſins, whilſt their Prieſts preach unto them for hire, <hi>and they love to have it ſo:</hi> This is their very end, and the very end of theſe things; and while people are giving ear unto you, it will never be otherwiſe: For its thus; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> they ſteal the words of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and of <hi>Jerome,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe, Auguſtine,</hi> and the like, and you ſteal it from them, and the people from you, and ſo what they have of you, is at the third and fourth hand, though in another misformed and diſguiſed ſhane, whenas in the ground it is but the Baſtard of the ſame whore, which the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> ſo dandle upon the lap of the Beaſt, as though he were the true born heir of the Kingdom of God, whenas he is no more like him, than light is like darkneſſe, or Chriſt like <hi>Belial:</hi> And if people muſt needs be ſo in love with this (which you ſo cry up amongſt them), they need not go to the Pope, nor come unto you for it, but at an eaſier rate than they give unto you, they may have as good of their own; but freely they may have of the Lord that which is quick, living, and powerful, and will abide for ever.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is the advice and counſel of the Spirit of God unto all people whatſoever, for to come unto Chriſt the light of the world, who hath enlightened them with his true light, which makes manifeſt ſin and evil in their own hearts, to the end that thereby they might be taught, led, and directed in the way of God, which is the way of true peace and holineſſe, which is none of the hirelings wayes, for they ſay men cannot tread out of uncleanneſſe all the dayes of their lives. And ſo from the Lord, this is a warning and tender Viſitation of love unto you all in this City, or elſwhere, where this may come, who are not yet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55273:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſentangled from this curſed yoak of ſoar bondage, which men of corrupt minds have laid upon your necks, for filthy lucres ſake, and diſhoneſt gain, with whom you will ſuddenly be cut off, if you repent not with ſpeed.</p>
            <p>AND now you who are the Magiſtrates of this City of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol,</hi> is it not a heart-reſenting matter unto the upright ſoul, for to ſee and ſeriouſly conſider the ſad event, which this impoſing of Oaths hath wrought in this Nation, inſomuch that few there be in it who have had any conſiderable name, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect therein, either in Civil or Eccleſiaſtick affairs, but have been (for the moſt part of them) perjured men? yea, few there are in this Nation, of one ſort or other, but are ſo, except it be a few people (who are called <hi>Quakers</hi>) who ſtand as your on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mark to ſhoot at, and whom you are ſeeking every way to enſnare in this thing (in matter of ſwearing) though moſt of you are not ignorant, how that for conſcience ſake they cannot ſwear at all, becauſe they durſt not break Chriſts command, nor the Apoſtles Doctrine, which was according unto it, who ſaid, <hi>above all things, my Brethren, ſwear not at all,</hi> (as well he might, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Lord and Maſter forbad it); and though it is ſo, that both by word and converſation, it hath been ſhewed often to you by us, yet you ceaſe not daily to ſeek to enſnare us thereby (ſo oft as opportunity comes into your hands for that purpoſe): And now let me tell you concerning this ſpirit that doth thus unto us, it is but the ſame which was in the <hi>Marian</hi> time, in which they were made to ſuffer death, rather than to defile their conſciences, (to the uttermoſt as to what they knew, and was made manifeſt in that day unto them); for when their bloody adverſaries could anſwer them no way, or at leaſt, when they would make ſhort work with them, preſently they would queſtion them concerning the Sacrament of the Altar, as you do unto us concerning the Oath of Alleginnce and Supremacy, all which, in the ground, is but one and the ſame ſpirit (that act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt us and them), though under ſeveral prerences; for which God did plead with them, and brought them down ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly out of their bloody Prelatical Seats; which I deſire may
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55273:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>be a warning unto you, for I did never ſee the Lord acquit the guilty and condemn the innocent, for <hi>he is juſt and righteous alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> And ſurely, I do believe ye cannot be ſo blind, as not to ſee the Prelatical Lordly ſpirit intruding it ſelf amongſt you, when your high Prieſt ſtands faſt in your Hall before you and all the people, laid hold on me with his own hands, and ſaid, I ſhould not have liberty to ſpeak there. You may ſee by this, whether he that is ſo devoted to a Surplice, would not alſo come to wear a Cardinals Cap, and ſo would turn black into red (if that way were but made for him), let the upright in heart, and unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd Reader judg.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall in the fear of the Lord propound ſome few Queries unto you, and ſhall leave and recommend them to Gods witneſſe in you all to judg, and alſo to anſwer the truth of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt, ſeeing Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Tree may be known by its fruit,</hi> whether or no this hath not been an evill fruit, brought forth by an evil Tree, <hi>(to wit)</hi> the impoſing of Oaths upon a people or Nation, ſeeing that few that be in this Nation did ever keep them; by which means they come to be worſe than the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, who are reputed only to be ſayers, and not doers; but theſe ſwear, and do not, by this means they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, not only falſe ſayers, but ſwearers alſo, againſt whom the Lords hand is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether this be not another Branch, ſpringing forth of the ſame curſed Root, That honeſt upright men ſhould be in danger of loſing their Eſtates, by the Oaths of them, who matter little, where, and what they ſay or ſwear? and whether many more have not been wronged by this way of proceeding, than have been righted otherwiſe, let Gods pure witneſſe in all judg, ſeeing the evidence of ſuch as will but ſwear, though a common ſwearer (in Whore-houſes and Taverns, and in his familiar communication) will ſooner be taken, than the Teſtimony of him who fears an Oath, becauſe he fears the Lord, and keeps to yea and nay, in all his communication.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55273:18"/> 4. And ſeeing that ſo many have ſworn for and againſt the King and others in Authority in this Nation, how can you put confidence in ſuch, ſeeing it hath bound men ſo little, as this Nation above all other Nations hath ſeen, to their ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</p>
            <p>And it being ſo, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That an Oath was amongſt men for the ending of ſtrife,</hi> whether then it doth not plainly betoken a people not to be out of ſtrife, who are found in that practiſe, and ſo conſequently no Chriſtians? for they love him, and keep his Commandments, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all; and if any man ſue thee at the Law for thy Cloak, give him thy Coat alſo:</hi> And if all were come to live in this Chriſt-like life, and Doctrine, what need would there be of ſwearing, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that evil is not to be overcome, but by this good and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent life, in which, if one be ſmitten on the Cheek, there is readineſſe to turn the other alſo?</p>
            <p>And laſtly, I query this of you all, Whether or no it be not an evil in all thoſe, who willingly go to enſnare any upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſeeing and knowing beforehand that they cannot ſwear?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:55273:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To you who are Biſhops, Arch-Biſhops, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens, Prieſts, or others, who are counted as the Heads and Teachers of the people now in <hi>England,</hi> I ſhall in the fear of the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto you a few Queries for you to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, how, where, and when you can, that ſo the people might come to underſtand, how, and by what means you are ſet to be their Teachers, and your Commiſſion thereunto.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1.</head>
            <p>FIrſt I query of you, why, and wherefore ye ſeem to make ſuch a difference between the Pope, and his Miniſtry, and yours, ſeeing that both your Call and Maintenance are one in the ground, that is to ſay, made by the will of man, and maintained both by one Law and manner of maintenance? and if it be not ſo, prove the contrary, and you will put and remove doubts out of the minds of people, and will alſo ſatisfie many concerning you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shew us who are your Authors for theſe things you now practiſe in your Churches, if the Pope was not, <hi>(to wit)</hi> your Childrens Baptiſms, Sacraments, Bels, Surplice, Organs, and for your ſinging <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms? anſwer plainly, without any eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſeeing you ſay, that mens ſalvation depends thereon; and alſo concerning your Letany, Collects, and your dividing the Scriptures in pieces &amp; parcels, to be read at ſuch &amp; ſuch times; I ſay, if they come not from the <hi>Romane Catholick,</hi> ſhew us from whence then theſe diſtinctions of Pariſhes, Church-yards, and Churches, ſhew us, I ſay, from whence had you your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and others, for theſe things? and if the Popes were not,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55273:19"/>prove it otherwiſe, and in ſo doing you will ſatisfie many, for many of the people in this Nation are jealous, as well they may, how that the Popes and their Counſels, were the firſt Couſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Ordainers of theſe things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether or no you do own ſuch a thing, as that God will teach his people himſelf? if ſo, then why do not you let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alone unto the Lord, to be taught of him, and ceaſe taking theſe great ſums of money, under a pretence of doing that which only and properly belongs unto the Lord? Give in your anſwers in plainneſs, hat ſo thereby we may prove whether you are approved Miniſters of Chriſt; but if you cannot prove your ſelves ſo to be, then it will be time, yea, and high time for people to draw off from you, and ceaſe giving their money for that which is not bread, and ſpending their time any longer about you.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Seeing that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin,</hi> then, whether or no, ye do not ſin, and cauſe the people to ſin, by going about to compel them by a Law, to conform unto that, which they are not perſwaded in the Faith to be according to the mind of God; for if they were perſwaded in their own hearts, (as the Apoſtle ſaid they ſhould be) then what need would there be of your compelling of them? and whether or no (it being ſo) it will not be your great ſin, thus to go about for to make the people ſin by a Law, ſeeing that it is ſo, that though one man ſhould be required to do a thing by the expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and movings of God, if another ſhould go about to do the like, and not be required of the Lord to do it, it would be ſin unto him? (I ſpeak in relation to the worſhip of God) and if it be not ſo, prove the contrary by plain Scripture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wreſting, if you can.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether, according to the Scriptures, ye own, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one hath the manifeſtation of the Spirit given them to profit withall? If you ſay you do, then tell me, why do ye, or indeed how durſt ye go about as ye do, to limit the ſame in people, and to appoynt them how much they ſhall hear, and how long you ſhall pray and ſpeak unto them (as you do by an hour-glaſs)? and tell me whether there can be blaſphemy in a higher nature
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55273:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>than this, for to limit the Spirit of God to ſo many words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (in ſuch and ſuch a form, time, and place.) O bluſh and be aſhamed for theſe things, and repent (if you cannot clear your ſelves from being the very men who are guilty of theſe things, as I know you cannot at all.)</p>
            <p n="6">6. VVhether or no you your ſelves would not have the free liberty and exerciſe of your Conſciences towards God, freely to do what you in your ſelves are perſwaded for to be of God in your own hearts? why will ye not allow the ſame liberty unto others, ſeeing that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>that every one muſt give an account of themſelves to the Lord, and every man muſt dye for his own iniquity?</hi> and whether or no it can truly be ſaid, a man is a Chriſtian indeed, until he come unto this life, <hi>(to wit) to do unto all men, as he would all ſhould do unto him?</hi> and whether the contrary may not be ſaid unto all who are contrary minded, that is to ſay, no Chriſtians, whether it be found in you, or any other (whatſoever they profeſs themſelves to be) upon the face of the earth?</p>
            <p n="7">7. And if it be ſo, that you cannot at all clear your ſelves from the guilt of theſe things, which are here queryed of you, but are found guilty of them, then, whether or no a man may not in the Spirit of ſound judgment (without offence to God, or juſt men) call you hireling Prieſts, falſe Prophets, blind Leaders of the blind, and ſay, you that are leaders, and thoſe that are led by you, will all fall into the pit of Perdition, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to go on in the pernicious way you are going in: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no one may not juſtly charge you to be Miniſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit, ſeeing that ye can limit your ſelvs to ſo many words, made ready unto your hands of other mens lines? which was not, nor is not the way or manner of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the free Spirit of God, which cannot be limited unto times, words, manners, perſons, nor places; but in whom he will, when he will, and where he will, he ſpeaketh as long as it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him that ſends it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. An Anſwer of theſe things will be exſpected from ſome of you, being I am made an offender by ſome of you for ſpeaking
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55273:20"/>ſomthing of theſe latter queries, and remain ſtill in the Priſon of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> a ſufferer for the Truth of God, and a witneſſe againſt all falſe Teachers, and hireling Prieſts, for ever; and ſo I ſhall conclude with this Query, VVhether or no it may not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſaid, that ſuch who take Tythes (under a pretence of a Goſpel Miniſtry) hold neither a Law, nor Goſpel, ſeeing that the Goſpel maintenance was to be free; and as under the Law <hi>Levy</hi> only was to have a maintenance out of it for his ſervice, and the reſt was for the maintenance of the father leſſe, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and ſtrangers, which you Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> are ſo far from, that you take it all your ſelves, and much more, where ye can get it, which is a great evil in you, ſeeing that Tythes properly belonged unto the Lord (in the time when they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the <hi>Jewes</hi>); but the Law being changed, the commandment muſt needs be diſanulled, and I am ſure you cannot find a new one for it ſince, unleſſe it be the Popes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Baily.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:55273:21"/>
            <head>The <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Servant of the Lord is gentle, and doth not ſtrive and wreſtle with fleſh and bloud (about outward things, and outward Obſervations), but hath the wiſdome from above, <hi>that is firſt pure, and then peaceable, and eaſie to be entreated;</hi> and when he hath given forth his Teſtimony <hi>for God,</hi> he leaves it to the witneſſe in all conſciences, by that to be believed; and until that be raiſed in the Conſcience <hi>for him,</hi> he is content to lye down in the ſuffering life, having learned of the Lamb of God, that pleads not his own cauſe, but committeth it to God: But men of ſtrife will have Oathes and Proteſtations to bind and confirm their power and Authority <hi>(over the Conſcience),</hi> becauſe they are wreſtling with fleſh and bloud, and with carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and their ſtrength of binding is only by the power of the Law, which Chriſt, the Oath and Covenant, of God hath put an end to <hi>(in them that believe in his name)</hi> that was made a Prieſt by the Oath of God, that could not ſwear by a greater than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>(as men verily ſwear by the greater),</hi> and by the word or voyce of the Oath is the bleſſing confirmed, <hi>in him that promiſed it to Abraham and his Seed, ſaying, ſurely bleſſing I will bleſſe thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee;</hi> which in the change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prieſthood could not be, in that they could not continue by reaſon of death; but by the two immutable things <hi>(wherein it is impoſſible for God to lye)</hi> the change might reſt on him, that was not made a Prieſt after the Law of a carnal Commandment, but the power of an endleſſe life, where the Prieſthood being changed, the Law is alſo changed: therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c. Let him that readeth underſtand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55273:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
